Finding Aid for John Sundwall Papers 1921-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Sundwall Papers 1921-1944
Sundwall, John, 1880-1950.
5 linear feet
Public health physician and director of the Division of Hygiene, Public Health, and Physical Education at the University of Michigan, 1921-1941, papers include correspondence, administrative reports and studies, working files, minutes of meetings attended, manuscripts of writings, and photographs.
86167 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Sundwall papers were donated by Mrs. John Sundwall (donor no. 3124 ) in 1954.
The collection is open for research.
John Sundwall, public health physician and educator, was born June 12, 1880 in Fairview, Utah. He was educated at the University of Chicago (B.S., 1903 and Ph.D., 1906) and at Johns Hopkins University (M.D., 1912). He taught anatomy at the University of Chicago (1906-07) and the University of Utah (1907-1910). After receiving his medical degree, he moved to the University of Kansas, where from 1913 to 1918 he was professor of anatomy, secretary of the Medical School and director of the University Health Service. In 1918, he went to the University of Minnesota as professor of hygiene and public health and director of the University Health Service. He served here until 1921 when he followed Marion L. Burton to the University of Michigan as professor of hygiene and public health and director of the newly created Division of Hygiene, Public Health, and Physical Education.
Prior to his arrival in Ann Arbor, the University of Michigan supported a quiltwork of health education opportunities with responsibility divided among a number of schools and colleges. Public health nurses, for example, were trained in the School of Education, while the Medical School, the College of Pharmacy, and the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts offered other required courses. Graduate training for other professional workers, such as health officers and sanitary engineers, was provided through the graduate school. Sundwall early on recognized the need for administrative reorganization and centralization of the university's health services and its curricula in public health training into a school of public health.
The process would be a gradual one and would consume most of Sundwall's professional life at the university. The Division of Hygiene, Public Health, and Physical Education to which Sundwall was appointed in 1921 administered five different activities: men's physical education, intramural athletics, women's physical education, the University Health Service, and the teaching of public health and training of health workers. Over the next two decades, Sundwall worked to streamline and knit together disjointed activities. First, in 1925-26, the division's physical education and intramural athletics responsibilities were transferred to the supervision of the Board in Control of Athletics, and the division was accordingly renamed the Division of Hygiene and Public Health. The most remarkable change, however, was the increase in number of courses being offered in public health, the number of faculty members available to teach, and the number of students receiving public health training.
One of his greatest accomplishments was his work in the establishment of a school of public health. At their August 1939 meeting, the Regents accepted the recommendations of the Division of Health Sciences that a School of Hygiene and Public Health be established. The School of Public Health as an administrative unit began with the school year in 1941. The school was helped immeasurably with funds for building and operations provided by the Rockefeller Foundation and the W.K. Kellogg Foundation.
Sundwall was also active with a variety of professional organizations: the American Public Health Association, the American Child Health Association, the Committee on the Cost of Medical Care, the Michigan Tuberculosis Association, and the President's Committee of Fifty on College Hygiene.
Sundwall retired as professor in 1949. He died December 13, 1950.
The collection has been grouped into the following series:
Biographical/background information
Correspondence
University of Michigan Division of Hygiene and Public Health
University of Michigan Topical
Organizations
Topical file
Writings
Photographs.
John Sundwall was an important figure in public health education, and his papers reflect his broad interests in this area. As a University of Michigan administrator and educator and as an involved member of various professional groups, Sundwall was a thoughtful leader in discussions pertaining to the kind of education and course offerings individuals in various public health positions should receive. More an educator and administrator than a researcher, Sundwall was a responsible and dedicated thinker in the development of public health as a respected profession.
The John Sundwall papers, covering the years 1921 to 1944, consist mainly of records maintained by Sundwall in his capacity as director of the University of Michigan Division of Hygiene and Public Health. There are no papers prior to his coming to Michigan in 1921 and only scattered papers after 1941 when the School of Public Health was established.
The Sundwall collection consists of correspondence, administrative reports and studies, working files, minutes of meetings attended, manuscripts of writings, and photographs.
The collection has been grouped into the following series: Biographical/background information, Correspondence, University of Michigan Division of Hygiene and Public Health, University of Michigan Topical, Organizations, Topical file, Writings, and Photographs.
Sundwall, John, 1880-1950.; Committee on the Costs of Medical Care.; Good Teeth Council for Children.; Presidents' Committee of Fifty on College Hygiene.; Committee on the Costs of Medical Care.; United States. Public Health Service.; University of Michigan. Division of the Health Sciences.; University of Michigan. Division of Hygiene and Public Health.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. University Health Service.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Children--Health and hygiene--United States.; Health education.; Hygiene.; Physical education and training.; Public health--United States.; Tuberculosis.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Sundwall family.; Sundwall, John, 1880-1950.; Sundwall, Mary.; Germany.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Portraits.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/background information
  Biographical/background information (2 folders) is an artificially created series of information regarding JS's professional activities. Included is correspondence regarding his appointment to the University of Michigan in 1921, a vita, and a memorial booklet published after his death.
  - Various (Box 1)
    (includes vita and memorial booklet)
  - Correspondence regarding appointment to the University 1921 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1921-1939, 1 linear foot
  Correspondence (1921-1939;) is a fragment of what once must have been a larger file. There are both chronological gaps and missing files from alphabetically arranged sequences. The files are arranged chronologically and then within that alphabetically. The files include correspondence with colleagues, students, and professional associates. Topics include public health, the development of public health curriculum, and the training of public health workers. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
  - 1921-1922, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1923, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1924-1925, 4 folders; through letter J only (Box 1)
  - 1926, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1928-1929, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1934, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1935-1936, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Division of Hygiene and Public Health 1922-1941
  (formerly the Division of Hygiene, Public Health, and Physical Education)
  University of Michigan Division of Hygiene and Public Health (1922-1941; .5 linear ft.) is an alphabetically arranged series of materials relating to Sundwall's administration of the division. The minutes of staff meetings (1937-1941) are of interest for their documentation of the years immediately preceding the establishment of the School of Public Health.
  - Building plans 1922-1936 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, etc. 1932-1939 (Box 2)
  - History of its establishment circa 1928 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Hygiene, Second Annual Conference on (1941) 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of staff meetings 1937-1941, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Personnel
    - Chope, H.D. 1940 (Box 2)
    - Hall, Marguerite 1940 (Box 2)
    - McLaughlin, Allan 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Survey of college registrars re organization of sciences in their colleges 1936 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Topical 1926-1944, 1 linear foot
  University of Michigan Topical (1926-1944; 1 linear ft.) consists of files relating to the university that have been placed into an alphabetical topical file. The series consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, and background materials. The files concern Sundwall's activities with other U-M units, notably the School of Education, the Health Service, and the Division of Health Sciences. There are also files relating to the establishment of the School of Public Health. In addition, of interest are files pertaining to the removal of university intramural athletics from the control of the Division of Hygiene and Public Health.
  - Course descriptions and approval for courses (Box 2)
  - Course syllabi, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Curricula-Hygiene, public health, etc. (Box 2)
  - Curricula (proposed course in public health engineering) 1937 (Box 2)
  - re Day Report 1926-1930 (Box 2)
    (removal of intramural athletics from the Division of Hygiene ...)
  - Education, School of
    - Correspondence, etc. 1932-1939 (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate Activities and Programs Committee 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Extension Division 1932-1939 (Box 2)
  - Extramural Services, Division of (include wartime physical preparedness) 1941 (Box 2)
  - Graduate School 1938-1944 (Box 2)
  - Health Sciences, Division of
    - Minutes of the meetings 1935-1942
      - 1935-1940, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Auxiliary Health Sciences 1938 (Box 3)
    - re Organization of School of Public Health, and relation of University's Health Service to the Division 1941 (Box 3)
    - Summary of transactions 1935-1942 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1937-1940 (Box 3)
  - Health Service
    - Criticism and evaluation circa 1927-1928 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, etc. 1932-1939 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Monthly reports 1933-1944 (Box 3)
    - Procedures 1928/29-1933/34 (Box 3)
  - Honorary degrees 1936-1942 (Box 3)
  - Institute of Public Policy and Social Administration 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Intramural Athletics, Dept. of 1933 (Box 3)
  - Medical School 1932-1943 (Box 3)
  - Mental hygiene 1928-1930 (Box 3)
  - Physical therapy 1938 (Box 3)
  - Postgraduate public health education 1933 (Box 3)
  - Public Health Assembly 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Public health laboratory/sanitary biology courses 1935-1939 (Box 3)
  - Public Health, School of
    - Establishment of 1938-1940 (Box 3)
    - General 1942 (Box 3)
  - Public Health Training courses 1926-1931 (Box 3)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Parran-Farrand study of schools of public health 1938-1939 (Box 3)
  - Summer Session 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Survey undertaken regarding doctorate in public health 1926-1930 (papers about) (Box 3)
  - Training of Teachers, Joint Committee on 1938-1941 (Box 3)
  - Venereal Disease Control Program 1938-1940 (Box 3)
- Organizations 1921-1942, 2 linear feet
  Organizations (2 linear ft.; 1921-1942) is an alphabetically arranged series of files relating to Sundwall's varied and productive involvement with professional associations. Of greatest bulk are files from his years of service with the American Public Health Association, especially its Committee on Professional Education. Other files of substance relate to the American Child Health Association, the Committee on the Cost of Medical Care, the Good Teeth Council, the Michigan Tuberculosis Association, and the President's Committee of Fifty on College Hygiene.
  - American Association of School Physicians 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors 1938 (Box 3)
  - American Child Health Association 1923-1934, 5 folders (Box 3)
    not all years represented
  - American Public Health Association
    - Correspondence, etc. 1924-1934
      - 1924-1925 (Box 3)
      - 1928-1929, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Committee on Professional Education
      - Correspondence, etc. 1935-1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Subcommittee on Education and Qualification of...
        - Dated files 1935-1937, 1939-1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Public Health Dentists 1937-1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Public Health Nutritionists 1937-1940 (Box 4)
        - Public Health Statisticians 1935-1940 (Box 4)
      - Subcommittees on Professional Education and Training of School Health Educators/Adult Health Educators 1936 (Box 4)
      - Joint Committee on Qualifications of School Health Educators and Adult Health Educators 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - American Social Hygiene Association, 1924-25, 1932-33, 1941-42 (Box 4)
  - American Society for the Hard of Hearing 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - American Student Health Association 1924-1935 (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Health Museum 1941 (Box 4)
  - Committee on the Cost of Medical Care 1930-1932, circa 1940, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Community Relations of the Curriculum, Committee on 1938-1941 (Box 4)
  - Conference of State and Provincial Health Authorities of North America 1937 (Box 4)
  - Conference: Professional Education and Training for Personnel for Health Education in Teachers Colleges 1938 (Box 4)
  - County Health Units 1938 (Box 4)
  - Delta Omega 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - Good Teeth Council 1934-1937, 1941-1942, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Merrill-Palmer Institute, Family Advisory Service 1939 (Box 5)
  - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company
    - Advisory Education Group 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Health Essentials 1927-1929 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Association of School Physicians 1934-1935 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Dept. of Health 1923 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Dept. of Public Instruction 1923 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Hospital Association 1931 (Box 5)
  - Michigan State Medical Society 1931, 1943, undated (Box 5)
  - Michigan Tuberculosis Association 1923-1926, 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Committee of Health Council Executives 1933-1937 (Box 5)
  - President's Committee of Fifty on College Hygiene 1925-1926 (Box 5)
  - Public Health Institute 1933 (Box 5)
  - Research Council on the Problems of Alcohol 1938-1941 (Box 5)
  - U.S. Public Health Service 1921-1926 (Box 5)
- Topical file 1926-1941
  Topical file (1926-1941; .2 linear ft.) consists of subject files on a variety of topics, such as medical preparedness during World War II and the proposed selection of V.A. Van Valkenberg to be Michigan Commissioner of Health.
  - Health education outline circa 1930 (Box 5)
  - Laymen as public health officials (resolutions about) 1926 (Box 5)
  - Maternity/child hygiene program (Box 5)
  - Medical practices act 1930 (Box 5)
  - Medical preparedness (World War II) 1942 (Box 5)
  - Public health engineering circa 1936 (Box 5)
  - Senate bills 1927-1933 (Box 5)
  - Van Valkenberg, V.A. (prospective commissioner of health for Michigan) 1940 (Box 5)
- Writings
  Writings (.2 linear ft.) includes reprints of articles Sundwall's reviews of manuscripts and books.
  - Reprints of articles, 1 expandable folder (Box 5)
  - JS reviews of manuscripts and books (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series including photographic prints and one ambrotype, consists of portraits of John Sundwall.
  - Portraits, 2 items (Box 5)